A Guide to the Virginia Geological Survey, Records, 1834-1903
Library of Virginia
- Series I: Correspondence of William B. Rogers, 1836-1903
  - Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Parkersburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, August 20, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Parkersburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, mentioning the length of time required to complete his survey of the Ohio River; discussing the coal seams in the region; mentioning a financial matter; giving news of his broken boiling point thermometer; and describing the sickness in the area which he had thus far escaped. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - I[srael] Slade, Christiansburg, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, August 26, 1840, I[srael] Slade, Christiansburg, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the intricate geology of the region from Buchanan to Christiansburg and asking for a letter and more detailed instructions as to what course to follow. 4 pp.
    - George W. Boyd, Warrenton, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 5, 1840, George W. Boyd, Warrenton, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing his increasingly severe attacks of asthma, his attempts to carry on his wrok despite his health, and his hopes of joining Rogers at the University in a few days. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Weston, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 8, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Weston, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning the difficulties encountered in making a section drawing of the strata along the Little Kanawha River and describing the geology of the region. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - I[srael] Slade, Wytheville, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 12, 1840, I[srael] Slade, Wytheville, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his two letters from White Sulphur Springs; outlining the difficulty of his work because of the rugged and wild terrain; and describing his route near New River. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Parkersburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 18, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Parkersburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing his work and the geology in the vicinity of Weston and Parkersburg and mentioning his plans for proceeding to Clarksburg and his need for money. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - Israel Slade, Jeffersonville, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 27, [1840], I[srael] Slade, Jeffersonville, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the geology of the area around New River, East River, Mercer County, and Abbs Valley. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 28, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, mentioning the lack of mail; describing his work along the route of the North Western Turnpike; discussing his plans to proceed to Morgantown; and asking again for money. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Morgantown, to William B. Rogers, Richmond, October 8 and 10, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Morgantown, to William B. Rogers, Richmond, commisserating with him over the sickness and death of George W. Boyd; describing the geology of the country between Bridgeport and Morgantown; mentioning a map of a portion of Harrison County which he had drawn; and describing the coal beds found on Scot's Creek. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - I[srael] Slade, Scott Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, October 12, [1840], I[srael] Slade, Scott Court House, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing his sufferings and those of his horse caused by the rough terrain between Tazewell Court House and Scott Court House and by the small amounts of food "served up in the most filthy and loathesome manner"; discussing the geology of Bear Town, Baptist Valley, and the Clinch River area; and mentioning a man he met named Wells who was examining coal seams and claimed to be employed by the state. 4 pp.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Monongalia County, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, October [17], 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Monongalia County, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing his exploration of Decker's Creek and the iron ores found there and revealing that he had hired Moses Wells, a resident of the area, to assist him. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Smithfield, Monongalia County, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, October 29 and November 1, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Smithfield, Monongalia County, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, mentioning that he has completed a section drawing from Morgantown to the headwaters of Scots River; describing iron ore and coal seams found in the vicinity of Henry Clay Furnace and a forge near Ice's Ferry; stating that he has traced the strata of the area around White Day Creek; and telling of his need for more money and relief from foul weather. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - I[srael] Slade, Wytheville, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, October 31, 1840, I[srael] Slade, Wytheville, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of Rogers's letter of September 28; answering, in response to Rogers's question, that he had filled almost five boxes full of specimens; and discussing the relative heights of Balsam Mountain and the Peaks of Otter and the cold weather. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Palatine Hill, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, November 14, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Palatine Hill, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing Rogers that he had gathered enough data for a section drawing of the Monongalia River region about 25 miles long and stating that the weather had turned so cold that he was about to start for the University but would need more money first. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, November 21, 1840, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of Rogers's letter of November 10 and the enclosed check and announcing his intention to complete the tracing of the Morgantown Coal Seam despoite the increasingly disagreeable weather. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - I[srael] Slade, Charlottesville, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, December 16, [1840], I[srael] Slade, Charlottesville, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, asking Rogers to make arrangements for him to draw his salary since deep mud on the road prevented Slade from coming himself. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, December 21, 1840, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter of December 17 concerning Israel Slade's salary; expressing his regrets over Rogers's ill health; and voicing his fears of "great curtailments" in spending by the General Assembly. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, to Henry D. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, December 22, 1840, William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, to Henry D. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, informing him that Israel Slade is about to leave for Philadelphia with iron ore samples for analysis, that Slade is highly nervous and needs adequate space in which to work, and that their brother Robert Rogers might "understand best how to get along with him"; wishing James or Robert Rogers might aid in the analysis; commenting on the coal fields near Richmond; noting that he always fretted over observations omitted by his assistants in the field and felt that he could satisfy his mind more with one week of his own field work than with "months" of that done by his assistants; worrying about the lack of news from Richmond on the fate of the survey in the General Assembly; and referring to family matters. 4 pp. [draft or copy?]
  - Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - W. H. Brown, Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, March 13, 1841, W. H. Brown, Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, advising him that before the Board of Public Works can pay the amount due Rogers as administrator of George W. Boyd's estate, he must submit an affidavit as to the date of Boyd's death; stating that the health of Brown's farther (James Brown, Jr.) is improving; and informing him that the survey survived for another year by a close vote in the House of Delegates, but that it had not yet passed in the Senate. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - Temple Gwathmey, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, March 19, 1841, Temple Gwathmey, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, saying that he had heard that Rogers's report concerning the coal of Chesterfield County placed the coal taken from Mr. Heth's deep mine in a category inferior to any other south side coal; that it was the impression in Richmond that Heth's coal was in fact superior rather than inferior; that there may have been an error in the Printing of Rogers's report; that if such was the case it should be corrected through early publication in the newspapers; and that Gwathmey would be glad to see to this correciton for Rogers. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - I[srael] Slade, Pittstown, New York, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, March 20, 1841, I[srael] Slade, Pittstown, New York, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the rigors of winter in upstate New York and believing that spring was well advanced in Virginia; revealing that he had spent so much time in the company of his friends over the winter that he had hardly thought of geology; and regreting that the snow has prevented him from examining the strata in his neighborhood. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., McGee's Inn, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 29, 1841, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., McGee's Inn, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, mentioning a letter he forgot to mail and asking for a copy of Rogers's report for 1837-1838. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - Evan T. Ellicott, Monogalia Iron Works near Morgantown, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 1, 1841, Evan T. Ellicott, Monogalia Iron Works near Morgantown, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, stating that he had read Rogers's last report and found it of great practical interest since he is engaged in iron manufacturing; that Caleb Briggs, Jr., had examined the area near the iron works last season; that a vein of hematite ore had been found on a hill near the Henry Clay furnace; that he would like to have a geologist come to examine the cleft in Laurel Mountain made by Cheat River, while Ellicott was at the iron works; and offering to send a sample of the hematite ore to Rogers. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 3, 1841, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing him that his and Israel Slade's claims had been allowed and the money deposited and that his brother James B. Rogers had been appointed assistant geologist effective May 1. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - I[srael] Slade, N. W. Turnpike at Kuykendall's, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 8, 1841, I[srael] Slade, N. W. Turnpike at Kuykendall's, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, giving an account of the observations made by Slade and Caleb Briggs, Jr., on their route from Massanutten Mountain through Winchester to Kuykendall's. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 16, 1841, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, mentioning his journey from Winchester to Clarksburg in the rain and giving an account of the production of a salt well near Cheat River Bridge. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 1, 1841, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter of May 20; informing him that he had completed the tracing of the Morgantown and Clarksburg coal seam; discussing a fossil stratum which he had traced last season; mentioning his plans to proceed to Morgantown, hire Moses Wells again, and visit Evan T. Ellicott; and expressing his need for another boiling point thermometer and an efficient assistant. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - Israel Slade, Williamsport, Maryland, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 4, 1841, Israel Slade, Williamsport, Maryland, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter of May 17; replying, in answer to Rogers's question, that he had written Rogers twice in May; stating that he had visited the Massanutten Range; describing the mountains around Harpers' Ferry in both Virginia and Maryland; and informing Rogers that he had lost his letter of May 17 and asking him to repeat his instructions concerning the work to be done around Woodstock. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 8, 1841, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter of May 28, and informing him that he had deposited the salaries of Caleb Briggs, Jr., and Samuel Lewis in the Bank of Virginia; and adding a personal note concerning Brown's recent illness, Rogers's health, and the approach of the raspberry season, and urging Rogers to come to Richmond and visit him there. 2 pp. with address leaf. Samuel Lewis was appointed by the Board of Public Works on July 11, 1840, to be assistant geologist in the room of Charles B. Hayden, effective June 1, 1840.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 15, 1841, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Clarksburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing him that he had completed his survey along Cheat River near Ellicott's iron works and that he had hired Moses Wells as a guide; noting that he hoped to complete the work in Lewis and Randolph counties within six seeks; and givinig Rogers directions for joining him in Clarksburg. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - Israel Slade, Strasburg, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 21, 1841, Israel Slade, Strasburg, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, complaining about the heat and describing the geology of the country between Williamsport, Maryland, and Strasburg. 4 pp.
    - Thomas Ridgeway, Jr., Weston, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 27, 1841, Thomas Ridgeway, Jr., Weston, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, stating that he had broken his boiling point thermometer by setting it down next to a hornet's nest on a bank of the Monongahela River, then upsetting it when he was stung on the ear; asking Rogers to bring a new one if he came to join them; and requesting more money. 2 pp.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Weston, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 27, 1841, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Weston, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, seconding Ridgeway's request for another boiling point thermometer; suggesting places for a rendezvous; and describing the coal seam at Weston. 1 p. with address leaf. Thomas Ridgeway, Jr., was appointed assistant geologist on April 15, 1840, in the room of Israel Slade, who had been appointed to the assistantship resigned by James B. Rogers.
    - Israel Slade, Woodstock, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, July 1, 1841, Israel Slade, Woodstock, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing him that he had finished his survey of Cedar Creek and had boxed the fossils and other specimens for shipment; describing the geology of the area, some iron ore seen and collected, and the beauty of the country; and asking for more money. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Beverly, to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, July 14, 1841, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Beverly, to William B. Rogers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, acknowledging receipt of Rogers's letters of June 27 and July 5; giving a detailed analysis of the geology found between Clarksburg and Beverly; and noting that Moses Wells will soon be leaving him to attend to urgent business. 6 pp. with address leaf.
    - Israel Slade, Beverly, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, July 19, 1841, Israel Slade, Beverly, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning the safe arrival of the new thermometer and discussing the geology of the Little North Mountain range. 2 pp.
    - T[homas] Ridgeway, Jr., [Beverly], to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, July 19, 1841, T[homas] Ridgeway, Jr., [Beverly], to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, thanking him for sending the thermometer and mentioning his plan to obtain a letter waiting for him at Weston. 2 pp.
    - Israel Slade, Bath County, on Bull Pasture [River], to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, July 31, [1841], Israel Slade, Bath County, on Bull Pasture [River], to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the geology of the country between Tygart's Valley and Bath County; mentioning a climb to the top of some perpendicular rocks overlooking Seneca River; and noting the inaccuracy of current maps in delineating the topography of the Crab Bottom region. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Beverly and Weston, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, July [26] and August 1, 1841, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Beverly and Weston, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter of July 12; reporting that contrary to what Rogers supposed, the survey of Randolph and Lewis counties had not been completed, due to Moses Wells's leaving the survey; describing what remained to be done; and discussing his illness and his plans for completing the work remaining. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Weston, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, August 8, 1841, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Weston, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing him that he had almost completely recovered from his illness; presenting the points which must yet be examined in order to complete the survey of western Virginia; and suggesting a program to accomplish this. 4 pp.
    - Israel Slade, Panther Gap, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, August 16, 1841, Israel Slade, Panther Gap, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the geology of the country between Bull Pasture River and Staunton and the difficulties he encountered in trying to observe the strata between Great Cow Pasture Mountain and Jennings Gap; acknowledging receipt of his letter in Staunton; discussing the hospitality of some gentlemen in the neighborhood of Staunton who would like Rogers to come give a lecture on geology to them; and presenting a request form Mr. Dudley, tavern keeper at Jennings Gap, that he be paid for the use of a horse by James B. Rogers over a year earlier. 4 pp.
    - Israel Slade, Callahan's, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, August 30, 1841, Israel Slade, Callahan's, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, discussing the structure of Mill, Sideling, Walker's and Chestnut Ridge mountains near Cow Pasture River and describing the geology of the mountains and valleys between Panther Gap and Callahan's. 4 pp.
    - Israel Slade, Monroe County, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 2, 1841, Israel Slade, Monroe County, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, enclosing residue obtained by evaporating crimson sulphur water which Mr. John Mahon of Union would like for Rogers to analyze. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Lewisport, N. W. Turnpike, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 9, 1841, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Lewisport, N. W. Turnpike, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, announcing that he had completed the survey of the region; stating that almost all the area near Elk River had been examined and what remains will be inspected by Wells and Ridgeway; complaining that his health had been almost ruined by the hard labor in the field; mentioning the coal measures in Preston and Monongalia counties having been traced; and noting that he planned to write Rogers again in a few days. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - Israel Slade, Parisburg, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 13, 1841, Israel Slade, Parisburg, to W. B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing the geology of the country between Callaghan's and Parisburg. 4 pp.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Guyandotte, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, September 25, 1841 P.M., C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Guyandotte, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter of September 14; outlining his plans for Wells and Ridgeway to join him in examining the country around Guyandotte River, Logan Court House, Pigeon Creek, Charleston, Summersville, Point Ridge, the Falls of the Kanawha, and Lewisburg; mentioning the geology observed on the Little Kanawha and Elk rivers; asking for more money; considering having Wells examine a narrow coal basin in his travels; and giving news of Rogers's friends in the vicinity. 4 pp.
    - C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Lewisburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, October 17, 1841, C[aleb] Briggs, Jr., Lewisburg, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, acknowledging receipt of his letter containing a check for $75.; describing the travels of Wells, Ridgeway, and himself as outlined in his letter of September 25; and hoping to return to the University about November 1. 3 pp. with address leaf.
  - Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 1844-1903 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, January 23, 1844, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, recalling that Rogers had planned to communicate to the legislature his views concerning the final report on the geological survey; informing him that several prominent members of the legislature had approached him on that subject; and urging Rogers to leave "your darling University" for a few days as soon as possible to come to Richmond for a personal conversation with the members. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, February 25, 1845, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing him that the bill before the General Assembly for publication of his final report on the geological survey died for want of zealous support and giving news of the Brown family. 2 pp. with address leaf.